

School of Mathematics and Physics, The University of Queensland

■ daniel@vfryer.com | 😭 danielvfryer.com | 🖸 frycast | 💆 _frycast

Complex data analyses are used in every industry and scientific field, but so many of the results are unintuitive and difficult to interpret. My aim is to make complex models more transparent, understandable and explainable, through research at the forefront of explainable AI, as well as through teaching and communication in general. I enjoy writing code (including software packages and libraries) in R, Python and Julia. I'm comfortable working theoretically, but I always want to apply theoretical methods to important real world problems. Aside from research, I teach various courses, and serve as a council member and Early Career and Student Statisticians' Representative at the Statistical Society of Australia.

Education

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

PhD | Statistics and Mathematics

2019-Current

• Explaining, exploring and clustering with non-linear and complex data

La Trobe University Melbourne, VIC, AU

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE | MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS WITH FIRST CLASS HONOURS (WEIGHTED AVERAGE MARK: 97)

2014-2018

• Random fields: Long memory, and R for cosmology

Experience _____

Monash University Melbourne, Victoria, AU

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2020-Current

• Politics & International Relations

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

CASUAL INSTRUCTOR | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2020-Current

· Master's of Data Science project support

Auckland, Auckland Region, NZ **University of Auckland** COURSE INSTRUCTOR | NEW ZEALAND SOCIAL STATISTICS NETWORK

2018-Current

• Introduction to SQL for academics and professionals

La Trobe University Melbourne, VIC, AU

SESSIONAL LECTURER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS

2018-Current

• Master's level meta-analysis | Master's level database fundamentals

The University of Queensland

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU 2019-2019

• Digital phenotyping for transdiagnostic clustering and psychiatric prognosis

La Trobe University Melbourne, VIC, AU

RESEARCH SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2018-2019

· Spherical data analysis in R on the HEALPix grid

Service

Statistical Society of Australia Melbourne, VIC, AU

COUNCIL MEMBER | EARLY CAREER AND STUDENT STATISTICIANS' REPRESENTATIVE

2020-Current

Dimension Reduction and Meta Analysis Research Group

Melbourne, VIC, AU

MEMBER | WEBSITE MAINTAINER

Campus Consultancy

2017-Current Melbourne, VIC, AU

SENIOR MENTOR AND FOUNDING MEMBER

2017-2019

Research School on Statistics and Data Science

Melbourne, VIC, AU

PEER REVIEWER (3 ARTICLES)

2019-2019

Journal of Open Source Software	Melbourne, VIC, AU
PEER REVIEWER (1 ARTICLE)	2019–2019
Victorian State Emergency Services	Melbourne, VIC, AU
EMERGENCY FIRST RESPONDER	2017–2018
La Trobe University Mathematics and Statistics Society	Melbourne, VIC, AU
Vice President Newsletter Editor In2Science	2016-2016
MENTOR MATHEMATICS SCHOOL OUTREACH	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2015–2015
Awards	
Vice Chancellor's Sessional Teaching Award	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, NA	2020
Three Minute Thesis People's Choice	Saint Lucia, QLD, AU
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, SCHOOL OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS	2020
Pitching Research Competition Best Written and Oral Pitch University-Wide	Saint Lucia, QLD, AU
The University of Queensland, Business School	2019
Pro Vice Chancellor's Commendation (awarded four times) La Trobe University, University-Wide	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2018
Department Prize in Fourth Year Statistics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2018
David Myer's Medallion La Trobe's most prestigious undergraduate award	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, College of Science, Health and Engineering	2018
Silver Scholarship Community Involvement and Dedication to Mathematics	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University Student Union, University-Wide	2017
Department Prize in Third Year Statistics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2016
Prof CJ Eliezer Prize in Second Year Mathematics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2015
Prof Jim Morrison Prize in Chemistry Best Performing Student (awarded twice) La Trobe University, School of Molecular Sciences	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2014
La Trobe Award in Community Engagement Volunteer Efforts	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, University-Wide	2014
Publications	
Pipeline	
D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi	arXiv
K-MEANS ON POSITIVE DEFINITE MATRICES, AND AN APPLICATION TO CLUSTERING IN RADAR IMAGE SEQUENCES	2020
D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen	arXiv
EXPLAINING THE DATA OR EXPLAINING A MODEL? SHAPLEY VALUES THAT UNCOVER NON-LINEAR DEPENDENCIES	2020
M Terrett, D Fryer, T Doody, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi	arXiv
SARGDV: EFFICIENT IDENTIFICATION OF GROUNDWATER-DEPENDENT VEGETATION USING SYNTHETIC APERTURE RADAR	2020
HD Nguyen, DV Fryer	arXiv
A BINARY-RESPONSE REGRESSION MODEL BASED ON SUPPORT VECTOR MACHINES	2020

Published

D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko

The R Journal

2020

RCOSMO: R PACKAGE FOR ANALYSIS OF SPHERICAL, HEALPIX AND COSMOLOGICAL DATA

D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko

Astrophysics Source Code Library,

RCOSMO: COSMIC MICROWAVE BACKGROUND DATA ANALYSIS

D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen

Frontiers in Applied Mathematics

and Statistics

ascl:

2020

2020

2017

Research School on Statistics and

D Fryer, A Olenko

Spherical Data Handling and Analysis with R package rcosmo 2019

D Fryer, H Nguyen, P OrbanJournal of Open Source Software

STUDENTLIFE: TIDY HANDLING AND NAVIGATION OF A VALUABLE MOBILE-HEALTH DATASET

Presentations and events.

IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence Brisbane

K-MEANS ON POSITIVE DEFINITE MATRICES, AND AN APPLICATION TO CLUSTERING IN RADAR IMAGE SEQUENCES

Talk and conference publication

Statistical Society of AustraliaMelbourneEARLY CAREER INDUSTRY SHOWCASE, CHIEF EVENT ORGANISER2020

• 6 panelists, 180 attendees https://vimeo.com/ssavic/20200922-showcase

SHAPLEY VALUE CONFIDENCE INTERVALS FOR ATTRIBUTING VARIANCE EXPLAINED

Victorian Research Students Meeting in Probability and Statistics

Melbourne

EXPLAINING, EXPLORING AND CLUSTERING WITH NON-LINEAR AND COMPLEX DATA

• Building the Melbourne research student community

UQ Research Video Pitch St Lucia

FORECASTING PSYCHIATRIC SYMPTOMS WITH DIGITAL PHENOTYPING 202

• First prize. youtu.be/h-m8QwLq29Y

UQ Three Minute Thesis Presentation St Lucia

Machine Learning: The Big Black Box

• People's choice award. vimeo.com/434959101

RSSDS2019 Poster Presentation Melbourne

Spherical Data Handling and Analysis with R package rcosmo 2019

• Poster and Springer book chapter

UseR!2018 Conference Brisbane

COSMIC MICROWAVE BACKGROUND DATA ANALYSIS WITH R 2018

• R package published on CRAN. https://youtu.be/7KBsguOlEHs

Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute Summer Research School Melbourne

FUNCTIONALS OF LONG-RANGE DEPENDENT FIELDS AND HERMITE DISTRIBUTIONS

• Summer Research Scholarship recipient. vrs.amsi.org.au/daniel-vidali-fryer-2017/

UNSW Statistical Challenges in Astronomy Sydney

LIGHTING TALK: A NEW R PACKAGE FOR COSMOLOGY

• Fostering new collaborations in statistics and astronomy